Guide to the Records of the American Institute of the City of New York for the Encouragement of Science and Invention 1808-1983 (bulk, 1828-1940) MS 17
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Children's Fair Years, 1921-1983
  - Subseries 3: Administrative, 1921-1983
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1937 (Offsite-box 591, Box 339)
    - Membership, 1937 (Offsite-box 592, Box 340)
    - Requisitons, Purchase Orders, 1937 (Offsite-box 592, Box 341)
    - Annual Reports, Committees, 1937 (Offsite-box 593, Box 342)
    - Awards, Meetings, Committees, 1937 (Offsite-box 593, Box 343)
    - Correspondence of Various Subjects, 1937 (Offsite-box 594, Box 344)
    - Amateur Scientist Papers, 1937 (Offsite-box 594, Box 345)
    - Amateur Scientist Papers, 1937 (Offsite-box 595, Box 346)
    - Amateur Scientist Papers, 1937 (Offsite-box 595, Box 347)
    - Amateur Scientist Papers, 1937 (Offsite-box 596, Box 348)
    - Amateur Scientist Papers, 1937 (Offsite-box 596, Box 349)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1938 (Offsite-box 597, Box 350)
    - Checks and Vouchers, Financial Statements, 1938 (Offsite-box 597, Box 351)
    - Financial Papers, Membership, 1938 (Offsite-box 598, Box 352)
    - Membership, 1938 (Offsite-box 598, Box 353)
    - Membership, Correspondence, 1938 (Offsite-box 599, Box 354)
    - Committees, Club Activities, 1938 (Offsite-box 599, Box 355)
    - Adult Education, Clubs, 1938 (Offsite-box 600, Box 356)
    - Meetings, Special Interest Groups, Checks and Vouchers, 1938 (Offsite-box 600, Box 357)
    - Science Observer Papers, 1938 (Offsite-box 601, Box 358)
    - Science Observer Papers, 1938 (Offsite-box 601, Box 359)
    - Science Observer Papers and Amateur Scientist Papers, 1938 (Offsite-box 602, Box 360)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1939 (Offsite-box 602, Box 361)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1939 (Offsite-box 603, Box 362)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1939 (Offsite-box 603, Box 363)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1939 (Offsite-box 604, Box 364)
    - Checks and Vouchers, Purchase Orders, 1939 (Offsite-box 604, Box 365)
    - Requisitions for Purchases, Dues, Budgets, Subscriptions, 1939 (Offsite-box 605, Box 366)
    - Finances, Membership, 1939 (Offsite-box 605, Box 367)
    - Membership Applications, Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 606, Box 368)
    - Membership Applications, Correspondence, Associate Members Program, 1939 (Offsite-box 606, Box 369)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 607, Box 370)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 607, Box 371)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 608, Box 372)
    - Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 608, Box 373)
    - Science Centers, 1939 (Offsite-box 609, Box 374)
    - Science Centers, 1939 (Offsite-box 609, Box 375)
    - Correspondence, Annual Reports, 1939 (Offsite-box 610, Box 376)
    - Annual Reports, Meetings, Awards, Board of Membership, 1939 (Offsite-box 610, Box 377)
    - Members, Sponsors, 1939 (Offsite-box 378)
    - Articles, Science Center, 1939 (Offsite-box 379)
    - Science Observer Papers, 1939 (Offsite-box 380)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1940 (Offsite-box 381)
    - Checks and Vouchers, 1940 (Offsite-box 382)
    - Checks and Vouchers, Time Sheets, Budget Statements, 1940 (Offsite-box 383)
    - Membership, 1940 (Offsite-box 384)
    - "Clubs Dropped from Affiliation", 1940 (Offsite-box 385)
    - Correspondence on Various Subjects, 1940 (Offsite-box 386)
    - Annual Report, Meetings, 1940 (Offsite-box 387)
    - Marconi Memorial Scholarship, 1940 (Offsite-box 388)
    - Science Observer Correspondence (A-P), 1940 (Offsite-box 389)
    - Science Observer Correspondence (R-Z), 1940 (Offsite-box 390)
    - Science Observer Reports and papers, 1940 (Offsite-box 391)
    - Science Observer Papers, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 392)
    - Clubs, Publications, Meetings, 1941 (Offsite-box 393)
    - Membership Applications and Correspondence, 1941 (Offsite-box 394)
    - Membership Applications and Correspondence, Science Observer Papers, 1941 (Offsite-box 395)
    - Science Observer Papers, 1941 (Offsite-box 396)
    - Adult Members, Resigned/Dropped (A-H), 1941 (Offsite-box 397)
    - Adult Members, Resigned/Dropped (I-T), 1941 (Offsite-box 398)
    - Adult Members, Resigned/Dropped (W-Z), 1941 (Offsite-box 399)
    - Invoices, Bids, Accounts, 1942-1944 (Offsite-box 400)
    - Central Files, Annual Reports, 1944-1952 (Offsite-box 401)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)`, 1952-1961 (Offsite-box 402)
    - Central and General Files, 1962-1966 (Offsite-box 403)
    - General Files, AAAS Grants, 1966-1973 (Offsite-box 404)
    - Annual Reports, Accounts, General Files, 1974-1978 (Offsite-box 405)
    - Annual Meeting, Cancelled Checks, 1978-1981 (Offsite-box 406)
    - Deposits, Checks, General Files, 1981-1983 (Offsite-box 407)
    - Checks, [1930-1939] (Offsite-box 427)
    - Checks and Deposit Slips, [1930-1939] (Offsite-box 428)
    - Member Index Cards, [1930-1939] (Offsite-box 429)
    - General Mailing List (A-C), Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 439)
    - General Mailing List (C-G), Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 440)
    - General Mailing List (G-K), Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 441)
    - General Mailing List (K-M), Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 442)
    - General Mailing List (M-S), Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 443)
    - General Mailing List (S-Z), and Businesses and Clubs, Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 444)
    - General Mailing List of Businesses and Clubs, Index Cards, [1933] (Offsite-box 445)
    - Letter File of Names and Companies, Index Cards, [1844-1936] (Offsite-box 446)
    - Letter File of Names and Companies, Index Cards, [1844-1936] (Offsite-box 447)
    - The Science Observer, Expirations, Index Cards, [1930-1941] (Offsite-box 448)
    - The Science Observer, Subscriptions, Index Cards, [1930-1941] (Offsite-box 449)
    - The Science Observer, Subscriptions and Expirations, Index Cards, [1930-1941] (Offsite-box 450)
    - Science Leaflet, Subscriptions, Index Cards Vol. 13, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 451)
    - Science Leaflet, Subscriptions, Index Cards Vol. 13, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 452)
    - Science Leaflet, Subscriptions, Index Cards Vol. 14, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 453)
    - Science Leaflet, Subscriptions, Index Cards Vol. 14, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 454)
    - Science Leaflet, Subscriptions, Index Cards Vol. 14, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 455)
  - Subseries 4: World's Fair, 1935-1940
    This subseries contains information on the American Institute's children's exhibit in the Westinghouse Pavilion of the 1939 World's Fair, which was co-sponsored with the Board of Education of the City of New York. The activities were meant for children 12-18 years of age and included science laboratory workshops, Junior Science Congress lectures, a photography laboratory, and an amateur radio station. The exhibition consisted of a rotation of science exhibits (generally exhibits from previous science fairs) and live experiments being conducted before spectators. The American Institute created the exhibits to promote interest in the American Institute Student Science and Engineering Clubs and to generate support for science education. The theme of the exhibition was "Science Makes the World of Tomorrow."
    The subseries consists of many different types of material relating to the planning, design, and running of the American Institute's exhibit at the 1939 World's Fair. The subseries contains correspondence, student applications, budget information, planning notes, reports, and photographs. It also contains two World's Fair scrapbooks containing clippings, pamphlets, letters, and photographs documenting the American Institute exhibit at the Fair. Films about the fair are also in this subseries.
    - World's Fair Committee, General Files, 1935-1938 (Offsite-box 408)
    - Students, 1939 (Offsite-box 409)
    - Students, 1939 (Offsite-box 410)
    - Students, 1939 (Offsite-box 411)
    - Students, [1939] (Offsite-box 412)
    - Students, [1939] (Offsite-box 413)
    - Students, [1939] (Offsite-box 414)
    - Students, Sponsors, Budget, 1939 (Offsite-box 415)
    - Accounts, Exhibits, 1939 (Offsite-box 416)
    - Exhibits, Publicity, Lists, Membership, 1939 (Offsite-box 417)
    - Dr. Alexander Efron's Files, Correspondence, 1939 (Offsite-box 418)
    - General Files, Thank You Letters, 1939 (Offsite-box 419)
    - Students, 1940 (Offsite-box 420)
    - Students, 1940 (Offsite-box 421)
    - Sponsor, General Files, 1940 (Offsite-box 422)
    - General Files, 1940 (Offsite-box 423)
    - Equipment Files, Correspondence, 1940 (Offsite-box 424)
    - World's Fair Films and Pins, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 425)
    - World's Fair Scrapbooks, 1939-1940 (Offsite-box 426)
- Series III: Scrapbooks, 1845-1941
  The scrapbooks generally fall into two categories: scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings and scrapbooks containing various printed items (usually circulars, pamphlets, tickets, forms, and announcements). Most material refers to American Institute events and programs. In addition, a few volumes contain correspondence, mostly letters to members. A number of clippings scrapbooks deal specifically with the Institute's Farmers Club.
  - Clippings, 1845-1846 (Offsite-box 461)
  - Printed Items (circulars, pamphlets, tickets, forms), 1846-1856 (Offsite-box 461)
  - Printed Items (circulars, pamphlets, tickets, forms), 1857-1869 (Offsite-box 461)
  - Clippings (Farmers Club), 1872-1873 (Offsite-box 461)
  - Clippings (Farmers Club), 1874 (Offsite-box 461)
  - Clippings (Farmers Club), 1875 (Offsite-box 462)
  - Clippings, 1876 (Offsite-box 462)
  - Clippings (Farmers Club), 1877 (Offsite-box 462)
  - Clippings (Farmers Club), 1878 (Offsite-box 462)
  - Printed Items (circulars, tickets, announcements), 1878 (Offsite-box 462)
  - Clippings, 1881 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Clippings, 1882 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Clippings, 1883 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Press Notices. 53rd Annual Exhibition of the American Institute (Clippings), 1884 (Offsite-box 627, Volume 567)
  - Press Notices. 54th Annual Exhibition of the American Institute (Clippings), 1885 (Offsite-box 627, Volume 568)
  - Printed Items, 1890-1893 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Clippings, 1897-1919 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Printed Items (programs, tickets, announcements), 1900-1902 (Offsite-box 463)
  - Correspondence, Printed Items, Clippings, Flyers, 1923-1926 (Offsite-box 464)
  - Correspondence (letters to members), notices, 1924-1926 (Offsite-box 464)
  - Printed Items, Clippings, 1924-1926 (Offsite-box 464)
  - Clippings, Publications, 1925-1927 (Offsite-box 464)
  - Clippings, Correspondence (many relate to Centenary Dinner, 3/21/1928), 1927-1928 (Offsite-box 465A)
  - Clippings, Printed Items, Correspondence, Invitations, 1927-1928 (Offsite-box 465B)
  - Junior Institute Program, Correspondence, Events, March of Science Copies, 1932-1933 (Offsite-box 465A)
  - Photographs, 1938-1939 (Offsite-box 465B)
  - Blank, 1940-1941 (Offsite-box 465B)
- Series IV: Pamphlets and Publications, 1829-1941, n.d.
  - Subseries 1: American Institute Pamphles and Publications, 1829-1941
    This subseries contains publications of the American Institute. These include the nineteenth century Journal of the American Institute (Vol. I-IV, 1835-1839); Annual Fair publications (i.e., premium lists); printed addresses on topics such as agriculture, gardening, sanitation; and annual reports and proceedings. In addition, material from the 1890s concerns photography and the American Institute's photographic salon. Bound Transactions of the American Institute cover the years 1847 to 1872.
    Twentieth century material includes annual reports, items related to the annual fairs, and material from 1930s Children's Fairs and Salons of Photography. American Institute publications for children and young adults include Science Leaflet (Jan. 4, 1934; Sept. 14, 1939-May 8, 1941), Amateur Scientist (May 1937-March 1938), Science Observer (Dec. 1938-July 1941), and March of Science (Sept. 17, 1932-Feb. 23, 1937).
    - American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, 1829-1847 (Offsite-box 466)
    - American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, 1847-1925 (Offsite-box 467)
    - American Institute Pamphlets and Publications (contains Science Leaflet, Amateur Scientist, Science Observer, March of Science), 1926-1941, n.d. (Offsite-box 468)
  - Subseries 2: Non-American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, 1933, n.d.
    This subseries contains publications not produced by the American Institute, including books and publications from the institute's private library.
    - United States Daily (oversize), 1933 Feb. 14 (Offsite-box 458)
    - Non-American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 469)
    - Non-American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 470)
    - Non-American Institute Pamphlets and Publications, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 471)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 472)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 473)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 474)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 475)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 476)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 477)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 478)
    - Non-American Institute Books, [1828-1920] (Offsite-box 479)
- Series V: Visual Materials, 1926-1927, n.d.
  This series contains mostly photographs and prints, the bulk of which are oversize or were removed from frames. These include photos of American Institute fairs and exhibits, experiments and equipment; portraits of scientists, museum curators, and science industry personnel; photos of American Institute buildings; a group portrait of the Junior Radio Club; photos of a diagram of the 1939 World's Fair; and photos of airships and mines. The bulk of photographs are undated, probably circa 1920s-1930s. Prints are generally mounted nineteenth century newspaper sketches. Also included are photostats and carbon stencils.
  This series also contains framed portraits of American Institute presidents:
  A. Cressy Morrison, 1930-1932
  H. Horton Sheldon, 1932-1934
  Alfred Knight, 1934-1936
  Robert T. Pollock, 1936-1940
  - Scrapbook of Fair Photographs (oversize) (Offsite-box 457)
  - Posters, "Exposition of Inventions" (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Broadside, "Play Golf" for Exhibition (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Images made from Printing Blocks (see Box 484) (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Smithsonian Institute Broadside (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Colorlog (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Pencil Illustration (oversize) (Offsite-box 458)
  - Photographs and Prints (Offsite-box 480)
  - Photographs and Prints (Offsite-box 481)
  - Framed Portraits of American Institute Presidents (Box 482)
  - Photostats and Carbon Stencils (Offsite-box 483)
- Series VI: Artifacts, n.d.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains various American Institute artifacts. Included are pins, ribbons, medals, and medal cases; a nineteenth century ballot/ticket, voting and cash boxes; printing blocks and wax seals; exhibit labels; and a letter opener.
  - Printing blocks, n.d. (Offsite-box 484)
  - Ballot Box, n.d. (Offsite-box 485)
  - Voting and cash boxes (Offsite-box 486)
  - Wax seals, n.d. (Offsite-box 487A)
  - Wax seals, n.d. (Offsite-box 487B)
  - Wax seals, n.d. (Offsite-box 487C)
  - Letter opener, exhibit label, particle board, n.d. (Offsite-box 488)
  - Pins and Ribbins from Fairs 1928-1939 (Offsite-box 489)
  - Printing blocks (from 1985 accession), n.d. (Offsite-box 490)
  - Medals and Medal Cases, [1830-1890] (Offsite-box 491)